go ahead and uh flip the recording so we
will have a nice clean one for the
YouTubes welcome everybody to handmade
hero uh the live show where we code a
complete professional quality game from
scratch using absolutely nothing no
libraries no nothing uh so that we can
basically see how every little part of a
game works and uh I've said it multiple
times I'll say it again I think it's uh
absolutely crucial uh for a good
programmer's education to kind of go in
and just see how everything works and
really understand it uh before you start
to do things like using higher level
stuff or using libraries and stuff like
that and there's just not a lot of
material out there that kind of shows
how to do every last little thing so
that you can kind of fill in uh those
gaps uh sort of as you go and become a
better game programmer and so what we're
basically trying to do on this stream is
build a game where we build absolutely
everything uh and so far it's been going
pretty well uh We've basically gotten
through the win32 interface portion of
things uh we're at the point where we're
playing sounds and showing bit map um
stuff on the screen and abstracting both
keyboard and uh and gam pad input so
we're pretty close to being at the point
where we're going to start actually just
working on the game part of the game um
which is not too bad concering the fact
that it has been I guess let's see 17
hours uh which is not a lot of hours we
only do one hour a day uh so that is not
very much uh to consider how far we have
come and so I'm pretty happy with our
progress and I hope you are too today
our primary goal is to sort of finish
cleaning up the win32 input St stuff and
just get that nailed uh down so we can
kind of move on and forget about it and
also maybe start to take a look at
timing in the game Loop which is one
more uh thing that we've kind of got uh
that we've got sticking around that
needs to be uh cleaned up so I'm going
to go ahead and uh and jump in here uh
obviously for those of you who have
pre-ordered the game you have access to
the full source code uh if with the link
that you got in your email if you
download that uh every night it gets
updated so you should have a zip if you
look at what day we're on we're on 17
you should have a zip that has all the
day Source codes in it so you want to
unzip day 16 um because that is what I'm
starting with here on day 17 we always
start with the previous day source code
so if you want to follow along at home
unzip that day 16 uh and you will be
exactly the same place that I am right
now when I open this up so uh where we
left off let's just talk about that for
a minute basically what i' done is
inside wind main uh which is our entry
point I had gone and said well I want to
add keyboard uh input here uh and I just
kind of quickly um did a few things to
get us in position to finish it up today
basically what I did is I said well uh
inside our wind main we had a message
Loop where we basically processed our
messages from Windows and I moved that
out into its own function here it's
called win32 process bending messages
and basically what I do is every time uh
through here we ask Windows if there are
any messages to process and as long as
there are in our while loop we will
process those messages uh now I didn't
want to actually use use our window
Handler uh our our uh Windows callback
function basically for our window I
didn't want to use that to process the
keyboard input because I was pointing
out a very important thing about flow
control basically when Windows does its
call back we have no control over what
gets P to that function our this was our
window callback function here now we
need to have this window callback
function because sometimes Windows calls
our window function uh with stuff
directly like the WM paint uh message
will sometimes come in just completely
out of the blue it won't go through our
message processing Loop Windows uh knows
because we registered I don't know if
you remember this way back from like the
first first or second day I guess second
day probably uh Windows forced us to
register a thing called a window class
which talks about the window uh the kind
of window we're making and in that we
gave it a call back and it is actually
free to call that call back any time it
wants to so we pretty much have to make
sure that we handle some set of Windows
messages in here that can be dispatched
at any time however keyboard messages do
not seem to ever be dispatched out of
line like that they always go through uh
the actual proper message Loop uh with
our Peak message and so on so if we want
to we can process the messages right
here and just never bother to have
Windows dispatch them because normally
what would happen when it's not sending
out a band like that is Windows sends us
the message first in this Loop it allows
it to pull that message off the queue
and then it lets us tell Windows okay
now it's time to dispatch it to the
windows routine okay to to our window
handling routine so it's kind of a
little bizarre it's like we pull it off
we look at it uh we then tell it to
dispatch that would actually be a nice
way to go if it weren't for the fact
that windows can sometimes just sneak in
a call directly to our window so we have
to have the window proc there's nothing
we can do about that but what we can do
is for all the messages that don't get
spontaneously sent like that we can
choose to process them in here and
that's really nice because what it means
is we can actually just have this still
be in our standard control flow we can
control what gets passed to it uh so
it's nice and clean it can be more
functional and uh of course when mean by
functional we haven't really talked
about that on the stream but that's
something that's worth noting so I'll
mention it here and I'll mention it
again a couple times because it's
something worth
understanding when you're doing coding
there's kind of two general ways you can
think about a a given function uh even
though there always are functions in
programs uh if I have a function and I
will call this functional function let's
say this is a functional function and
then I have uh something which is a
procedural function or whatever you want
to call it function with side effects
let's say function with side effects
because side effects are typically what
distinguish something functional from
something
not uh what distinguishes two sets of
functions is whether or not into
functional or non-functional when we use
that term uh basically a functional uh
function is one which does not modify
anything uh other than the stuff that it
is passed and that it returns so basic
basically it is going to get some uh
some values which are not pointers to
things they're not references to stuff
like graphs that can be crawled or any
of this sort of stuff they are they are
actually getting in values which
themselves are not sort of writable
memory uh and then it returns uh
something that is the result of of
whatever it's going to do so you know
maybe it's going to do uh this sort of
thing right and I am going to return
that okay so this is an example of a
functional function it takes two things
in two things which it does not use to
go modify other stuff it returns integer
never touches any Global variables so
basically it is entirely uh it is
functional almost in the mathematical
sense uh that you would think of a
function in math where it takes
parameters in and it outputs a result
but nothing else changes the state of
the program does not change in any way
other than the fact that this result was
computed that's it uh now when you have
something called side effects in a
function it ceases to be functional and
basically what that means is if let's
say I did something like this and then I
had something like Foo star Fu and
here's my Foo right it's got some stuff
in it maybe it's got a pointer to a bar
and it's got an INT in it and it's got a
result and all sorts of things and in
here I just go all right um you know and
maybe I still pass the Y so you know I'm
going to go ahead and take the fu Arrow
result equals the X Plus Y and so on or
I might even do something where I look
at the bar
and I I find out you know if the bar Z
is equal to five I'm going to do
something right this is more typical of
C style stuff um and basically what ends
up happening right is you can see very
quickly that the understandability of
this function uh becomes much quicker
much uh more complex when I have uh sort
of things that fall out of what that
diverge from that functional style when
I'm not just taking some simple
parameters in and having a simple uh
return value come out I start to have a
lot of more complexity into what might
happen when you call this function right
like maybe this function is going to
write to F result maybe it's only going
to write to F result under some
circumstances so on and so forth and
basically what I've produced is
something that in order to understand uh
what happens when you call this function
you have to actually understand the
structure of the data of the program and
how it uh exists in memory you can't
just look at it trly and go oh I see I
pass it two things and back comes the
result that's all that's going to
there's nothing's going to change in the
state of my program the state of my
program is effectively immutable to this
functional function the program state is
identical to when I called it the only
difference is I got back a result that I
can now use to do something whereas in
this one the state of the the actual
data state of the program has been
mutated by the act of calling the
function and that's kind of what we mean
when we say side effects it's calling
the function changes the permanent data
store in the program in a way
that means that if you called it say
twice in a row or if you inserted a call
to it between two other calls those
calls themselves could also be changed
how they operate right two functions
with side effects getting called in
opposite orders for example might have a
different effect whereas two functional
functions called in opposite orders
can't because they don't change anything
so if I call a functional one functional
function and another functional function
uh I know that I could swap the order of
those calls for example and nothing
would change because the only state uh
that they're getting is what's passed in
the parameters so unless I took the
result of one and passed it to the other
one I know that they have no connection
to each other whatsoever and so there's
just a lot of things uh that happen when
you can boil something down to a
functional function um and there are
programming language that are all about
being almost entirely functional for
example uh like you know uh things like
ml for example or programming languages
based around this
concept it's a very limited way to
program because there are so many
options there are so many things the CPU
can do that are off the table now for
you um but if you are in a situation
where you can make things more
functional without sacrificing something
it is often beneficial to do so because
it makes the understandability of the
program and the reliability of the
program increase in most circumstances
because now there isn't this knowledge
of the state of the program that has to
be going through the programmer's mind
when they do things in order to make the
program work properly they can literally
just see a function know that when they
call it it does the same thing no matter
where in the program you are they don't
have to worry about setting something up
shutting something down all these sorts
of things uh and so what I typically try
to do when I am programming is I do try
to push towards functional when it is uh
not uh prohibitive to do so so what does
that mean it means passing things as
parameters rather than using Global
state it means passing things by value
rather than by reference if possible uh
and making them so that they're not
going to be changed by the function uh
it means limiting the access of
functions to only the things that they
need absolutely need to use uh so that
they're easier to understand and I never
really uh ever get to a point where my
code is super functional that never
really happens it's not the nature of
the kind of code I tend to write but I
do try to make I do try to follow those
steps to sort of increase increase the
functional of the program because every
little bit you do is a bug down the line
a readability plus down the line that
didn't happen whatever you know that
sort of thing a complexity down the line
that you didn't have to deal with and so
what I like to do here uh is basically
there's a a more complex program flow
thing that would happen the way that we
used to do things in our old um win32
window uh Handler
um sorry trouble finding it there in our
132 Main window callback If This Were
processing uh the keyboard messages here
right uh if this were passing the If
This Were processing those keyboard
messages it would have to have a place
to put them right it needs to store the
result of those keyboard operations and
in order to do that that means it would
have to have access to the input
structure but as you can see I can't
pass that in here I can't give it the
thing that it's supposed to be operating
on because Windows has defined the the
function prototype for this call and
there's nothing I can do uh to insert
myself in here so in order to get in
order to basically do the plumbing
necessary to get the keyboard uh the
basically the the place where the
keyboard results should be written into
this function would require a global
variable using uh the local storage in
the window itself using Windows to get
ins set of property for example I would
have to use something that is very much
not functional at all uh because it
would basically be something where the
um where the the state was completely
implicit and you just had to know oh hey
by the way the main W window call back
just imagine knows what controller to
write to and it got it from this Global
variable and hey don't worry about it
right and I don't like having things
like that so I can do much better uh by
pulling it out uh into a function that's
under my control uh because while again
it's not going to be functional at all
because it's using a message cue and
pulling messages off a CU so there's
nothing functional about this function
for the most part um but uh I can make
it into more of a stable functional uh
flow control where I'm still passing the
output Place uh directly in and it's
understandable very clearly
understandable in that functional way uh
it's it's much more easy to understand
for the programmer What's Happening by
saying when I do win 32 process messages
I just pass it directly where I want the
stuff to go and that allows me to use
this function anywhere I want to uh to
basically say here's where I want you to
put the stuff and anyone else could use
that to put stuff in a different place
if they wanted to and anyone who calls
it knows exactly where the results are
going they're not in this state where
they're like I don't know I said I had
to set a global variable first and then
it figured it out and so on
uh so something to think about something
to think
about people were saying on this I just
glanced at the chat just then they were
saying I was a little too loud uh we
could easily turn the oh you know what I
think this was not this was oh wait no
that's the microphone uh I think we
could set the microphone down a bit
though uh I'll do a quick mic check is
that is that better is that less clippy
when I'm talking what do you guys think
about that I'm going to I'm going to
this is an example of me talking as L as
I talk so there you can tell me in the
Stream and I'll glance back at it to see
if maybe that's a little bit better if
that's less clippy for people on stream
let me know if that's better or if it's
harder to hear me all right there we go
all right so now that you understand why
I did that uh what I do need to do now
is actually finish the actual keyboard
processing because we didn't actually do
hardly any of it we didn't actually do
the work of getting uh things into a a
good state for using the keyboard so the
first thing I want to do is I want to
kind of look through here and kind of
clean up the way that we're thinking
about input uh because it wasn't set up
uh particularly well uh in the first
place so the first thing I want to do is
I want to say all right let's just let's
just for now uh because like we said
when we get down the line later and the
game is more complete we will kind of
revisit how we're doing input and how we
map things and all sorts of stuff like
that but for now what I'd like to do is
say let's give the game basically uh
let's have the keyboard come in as One
controller like it's like a gam pad
right the keyboard comes in as a certain
controller it's controll Z let's say and
then the first game pad is controller
one and the second game pad is
controller two let's make it look like
that I think that'll be a sane way to do
it to start uh and then later we'll kind
of get into things maybe where we want
to do something a little more
complicated than that uh as as we see
what our game actually wants uh but I'm
going to go in here and basically say oh
and the other thing I should probably do
is put this there there we go so make
sure I don't put anything down in the
corner I always forget to put my little
blocker up so I remember not to put any
code in the corner so let's go in here
uh and just take a look at how we're
storing things uh basically we've got
four controllers uh mapped in here but
what I'd rather do is is up it to five
so have four gamepads and the keyboard
is basically how we'll do it uh and so
the keyboard controller will be
controller zero uh but then when we kind
of go in here and use these controllers
uh instead we're going to actually say
all right let's make this be controller
uh this is X input um I'm sorry uh
basically our controller index uh is
mapped differently uh so we'll say our
controller Index right uh is going to be
the controller index plus one because
we're basically leaving space uh for
that keyboard controller so now there
are actually five controllers in here uh
not not four so uh when we go in here we
will basically uh have to modify our
check for how many controllers we
actually think uh is the maximum so
basically what we need to do is we need
to say one for the keyboard plus the
xuser max count and then we'll just
double check that that all fits and then
off we go so that's actually what I
wanted to to do oops I spelled that's
good spelling after a good start with
our spelling today can't even spell so
that's good uh oh and this is something
that I think I forgot to do yesterday
you'll notice we have a um a uh a link
warning here so basically I showed
yesterday and I think some people missed
it because the stream dropped out and so
if you didn't watch the Youtube you
missed it uh I showed basically here how
to on the 32-bit build uh how to get it
working on Windows XP but you can't
actually use Windows XP uh builds if you
are doing um 64 bit because 64-bit uh
builds with the 64-bit compiler don't uh
run on the Windows 51 XP thing as far as
I know uh so basically what you want to
do is we actually want to have sort of a
32-bit build line and a 64-bit build
line and in the future what we're going
to want to do is actually build both
potentially uh but like I said I
couldn't do that yesterday because uh I
have to go do a bunch of stuff uh
getting extracting stuff from VC vars to
call the right compiler directly since
you can't use the same compiler to to
build both and all these other sorts of
things uh but basically what we we want
to do is say well there's going to be
two build types right there's going to
be one uh that's for win 64 and one
that's for win 32 so we could do them
like that but what I'd like to do is
most of the stuff is shared between the
two of them uh so what I'd like to do is
I'd like to just take a second and say
let's set a variable here uh that's
basically like um for now we'll call it
common flags and we'll kind of do we'll
do some more work with this in the
future but let's just say you know okay
uh we basically want all of this stuff
for now uh to be in our common flags all
of this stuff uh kind of comes in here
right that's our common uh common
compiler Flags let's say uh and then
we'll do common Linker flags that are
just the things uh that we actually
wanted to pass uh to the two different
parts so we grab that there put that up
there and say okay that's common Linker
flags and basically all I'm going to do
uh is say all right so this subsystem
piece we'll take that out of the common
and we'll stick it in only the 32-bit
version right uh and then this one here
will just be basically the same as that
uh only it won't have that one piece and
so then that'll let us do uh either of
them I believe uh oops it's not right
I'm
missing that is that right there we go
so uh basically all I did here is just
made two lines one for the 32-bit build
so basically we've got the 32 bit build
here uh and basically we've got the
64bit build here and they're going to be
exactly the same except for those those
things we might change some things and
in the future we'll make uh another
variable here for release flags as well
so when we want to turn on optimizations
we can do that uh but let's just do that
and get that out of the way all right so
now we've got our uh our controller um
as well I'm going to go ahead and make
sure that we didn't mess anything up
there because I kind of was um talking
about a ton of things there and hard for
me to pay close attention to what's
going on so I like to run the game
periodically to make sure I didn't do
anything horribly bad um all right so
now that we have this we need to
actually process our keyboard controller
for read and so what we need to do is
when we actually uh take the new state
of the keyboard controller what we
probably want to do is say that it
should actually um if if we look here
the way that I've got it uh we basically
want to preserve some of the State uh
we've got the uh the ended down thing
and we have to make sure that the ended
down um we have to make sure that if we
don't receive any keyboard messages this
Frame we are still accurately
representing the state of the keyboard
which is not something we're actually
doing um at the moment we always zero
out the state of the controller so if a
key goes down we'll receive a message
we'll set ended down to be correct that
we implemented uh but what we didn't do
is actually make sure uh that it would
then persist to the next frame so it
would still appear to be down uh and and
so that's what we have to actually
handle now so what we want to do uh
probably here is basically we only
really want to reset the half transition
count uh we want to leave ended down
basically the same uh so what we can do
we can do that to different ways I guess
what I'll do is I'll clear the keyboard
out for now um and I will um just Loop
over these buttons real quick here I'll
basically say that the button index for
the keyboard uh you know I'm going to go
over the array count uh of keyboard
controller buttons uh and from there I
will basically take each one of those
things and I will I will basically map
um I will map sort of the old one to the
new one so I've got the old input and
I've got old keyboard controller new
keyboard controller uh and basically
what I'll do is I'll zero the new one
and you can see what I did here was just
make a blank one and assign it to do a
clear uh and you see I did a zeroing
macro to do which maybe we'll do today
during the cleanup if we've got time uh
basically I'm going to come in through
here I'm going to take the old keyboard
controller uh and I am going to grab its
buttons uh here so I'm going to get its
buttons pull out the button in question
uh and I am going to make its uh ended
down uh equal to uh so I'm going to make
the new I should say uh equal to the old
one so this basically just copies
whether or not the key was down to the
new one uh so that way we know that when
we come in here our new keyboard
controller has the same ended down state
but we now know that the half transition
count is clear which is what we want
because we're supposed to count half
transitions per frame so when I come up
here uh into the the processing Loop and
I look at what I'm calling I'm calling
the win32 process keyboard message uh
basically what happens is I anytime I
get the message I change I increment
that half transition count and then I re
I set the ended down to the correct
thing so this basically just counts how
many times we changed it uh I can also
assert here uh that basically the new
state ended down is not equal to the new
uh is down type because remember we're
only supposed to be getting this
keyboard message if the state changed
because we very explicitly check for it
right here uh we basically say we're not
going to process the keyboard event if
it was just saying that a key was down
that was already down so that's a key
repeat message and we don't want to be a
slave to Windows key repeat settings or
do any stuff like that we want to take
that out of the equation entirely uh so
basically we just want to assert that we
didn't do something stupid because often
times in programming you will do
something stupid because you forget
what's going on or you make a change and
don't realize what's happening uh so we
want to assert here and just say hey
look we want to make sure that when we
get an is down message it's actually a
difference it's either if it's true that
it's down then it the key shouldn't
already be marked as down because our
half transition count would be wrong at
that point uh and and we also want to
check for the opposite if the key is
saying that it's going up we want to
make sure that it wasn't already up uh
so now when I do that uh and fix the uh
the bugs here the
typo
typos and there we go um basically all I
need to do is verify that that worked at
all we'll go in here and there you go so
that's me pressing the button just like
I would have on the controller and hey
it works perfectly uh now we need to
process the directional stick and that
brings up something that I've been
wanting to do for a while which is we
actually need to kind of finish all of
our directional stick stuff because our
Gamepad Direction STI stuff still had a
TOD do in it as well uh which is
basically that we had a um we basically
had a dead zone processing to do where
we didn't process The Dead Zone because
we didn't really talk much about what
the dead zone was Now The Dead Zone uh
is basically it it no not it is not a
game about zombies although with the way
the game industry is going these days it
will probably soon be a game about
zombies somebody out there right now is
maybe taking the handmade hero um
platform layer and is turning it into a
game about zombies called Dead Zone and
that is always a possibility but um
basically what um what I wanted to talk
about is The Dead Zone on a controller
and you can see here is my pink
controller um basically what happens is
these sticks uh you have to imagine
inside in fact this is translucent you
probably can't see it uh but inside
there's a you know that stick basically
connects to a circuit board and it's got
some Electronics in it uh I I think they
are usually potentiometers I don't even
know I'm not a hardware guy so to be
honest with you I have no idea what
actually goes on in there but what I can
tell you is that the accuracy on these
things is awful uh so basically even
though this is back at zero like we
would all think of that as not the stick
is not doing anything right now uh that
is actually not what the electrical
reading is on the stick the stick right
now actually thinks it's somewhere
entirely else uh and basically we can
even demonstrate that uh by basically
going like okay uh let's go in here and
set a breakpoint for example um
somewhere oops that's that's not good
what what's going on here I didn't mean
to actually modify my code uh yeah so
basically I've got the this the stick
the stick is back at its neutral
position I'm going to go in here to our
code and I'll just take a look at what
happens when we pull it right so I'm
going to pull it here we go let's get
down in here um so basically we pull
this thing uh and what did we actually
get back for our X and Y you can see
that they are definitely not zero right
there's noise in there uh and so the
location of the stick when it is quote
un quote centered is actually not zero
and that's not actually a bug that's
just how that's the tolerances for which
these controllers are designed to
operate like they aren't designed to
give back an exact zero when the thing
is centered they're designed to be
somewhere around zero when the thing is
centered so in order to correct for the
fact the player thinks the stick is
centered but the stick is not centered
what we need to do is apply a dead zone
which is a region around zero where we
will effectively consider it zero we are
basically widening our opinion of zero
uh and you can see that X input
basically defines these values that they
want you to use in order to be compliant
uh and you know so we will use them
basically what they are uh if I can get
the mstn documentation with them here
let's see hello come on there we go
internet Go Go internet um basically
what happens uh if I can scroll down to
there we go The Dead Zone here um so
basically what we want to do is we want
to use that dead zone this input Dead
Zone thing which they have they have
actually defined it again I don't know
why they actually it was their defined
to begin with I don't know why they did
that uh point being here are the dead
zone values right basically what these
dead zones are saying is that any value
for the left thumb stick that's left
less than 7849 short that's a 16 bit
value uh right so uh you can kind of
Imagine um what percentage that actually
is uh if we wanted to do the calculation
so oops Cal uh so basically uh if you
imagine
32768 is the maximum sign short value uh
negative uh that it would be and so if
we if we actually look at what
percentage that is 32768 if we say 7849
divided by
32768 like that uh you can see that
that's well you know if you look at that
number it's surprisingly large it's
somewhere between a fifth and a quarter
of the stick is just flat out being said
is is not usable right it's like there
the the Xbox standard I guess is
basically saying we are going to
manufacture stuff that is up to uh
almost up to um a quarter a a quarter of
the range is just gone right uh in in
any given Direction and it's even worse
for the right thumb stick that's even a
little higher that's closer to a quarter
right so that's uh that's let's see here
divided by 3 2 768
so that's actually over 25% so that's
just to give you an example of how large
that dead zone is it's big so what we
want to do here is we want to basically
just pretend that if we get values that
are that are in that range uh that they
are not really going to be considered uh
valid values we're just going to if
they're if they're inside that range
we're just going to treat them as zero
so in order to do that uh I'm not sure
exactly how I want to do that I did the
range mapping here I feel like they're
basically saying that this needs to be
applied in either direction they're not
really clear on the difference because
if you'll notice the negative range is
different than the positive range like I
talked before it's one greater so it's a
little odd that they're the same we
don't really know very much uh about it
so we're going to have to take their
word for it but it might be nice if they
had done a little more documentation
here to talk about the difference
between positive and negative in this
case uh because like I said uh-
32768 is a negative value 3276 seven is
actually the positive value right so
there's a difference in range there and
and we're off by one a little bit so
it's odd that they didn't respect that
but those are the dead zone values we're
going to use them the way they suggest
to use them uh basically what we're
going to do here is we're going to
change our processing to basically start
out uh by saying that the X and the Y
are assumed to be zero uh we will then
go ahead and access uh the
um excuse me uh we'll go ahead and
access these values uh we'll say if um
the uh oops if the pad uh well you know
what I can actually do it uh just like
this here so I can basically say this
whole thing is predicated on this being
lower uh than the dead zone in this
direction right like that and this thing
is predicated uh on it being higher than
the dead zone uh now I don't remember if
they said higher than the dead zone or
higher than or equal to they did say
higher
uh yeah now this is well that's an
interesting thing oh the oh it's a
magnitude check okay that's fine we'll
talk about that in a second all right so
anyway this right here is basically um
this right here is just saying all right
we were already checking so that we did
the divide by the right value depending
whether we're positive or negative uh
and if we look at what's Happening Here
we can basically say all right now what
we're doing is saying don't even set the
value of x unless the value on the game
pad is already less than the dead zone
for negative or already greater than the
the the um value for positive and so
it'll just leave it set at zero
otherwise right so you can kind of see
the way that that works right and then
similarly we can go down here and set
this guy uh and and do the exact same
thing this guy will just be um doing the
same thing this is our our left thumb
dead zone as well uh right like that uh
and Pad s thumb ly greater than and now
the only thing that we have to do is is
we have this we want like the negative
right we want it to be less than the
negative version of The Dead Zone uh so
we need to just stick a negative in
there right if that makes sense because
otherwise we'd be checking if it was
less than the positive value of The Dead
Zone which a negative value always is
going to be so we want to make sure we
catch the range on either side right so
that's that's really it um there wasn't
a whole lot else that I wanted to do
there but I just wanted to make sure
that we got that in there so we can get
rid of our to-do uh and then we can also
say well these two things look uh very
very similar right they're almost the
same so what we could do is we could
change this to a win through2 process X
input uh stick position right or or
stick value I guess we could call it um
and then we can go and say all right we
know that we would pass it uh the LX so
basically we pass it whatever the the
value is uh we'd pass it the the the
thumb uh Dead Zone value that it should
use uh and then we pass it uh basically
the the place to write that into uh
which actually is going to be a little
problematic for us uh because we need to
sort of group uh we need to group The
the left and the right stuff which is a
little tricky uh based on how we've done
it uh I could pass values to each
individual one uh maybe that's the
easiest thing to do uh or I can I can
sort of short circuit that process for
now and not go the full route and just
do this so what I could do is say is say
that right hopefully that makes some
sense uh so we'll basically say we'll
just use that same path and then down
here we would do you know this sort of
thing uh pad uh with the with the with
the ly doing the same thing there for
the dead zone and you'll notice we're
using the same dead zone zone for X and
Y which seems
weird but I guess that's how the
controller is supposed to work have the
same dead zone for both I don't really
know um but that that appears to be uh
what they are suggesting so I'm going to
go ahead uh and pull that out uh so that
we basically have a function that does
exactly what I just said uh here we go
into our utility function here just so I
don't have multiple copies of this
function uh and that is this so it's
going to look like like uh something
which basically just takes uh in first
the short I believe is what this is
defined to be it is a short uh is it
capital short I think is what they are
uh let's take a look um what is the name
here it
is um one of those State structures X
input State just want to ver verify that
it is a short Capital that's what they
actually are using for their 16 we could
use in6 if we wanted to but I want to
use the actual thing that they have
defined it to be so it's a short that's
what I thought uh so basically up here
uh we just want to take that short value
whichever one we're taking so this is
the uh the the value uh and then we are
going to uh take the dead zone uh value
as well we'll call that the dead zone
threshold and then inside the function
we just do exactly uh what we did before
um we basically now just use whatever
value was pass passed in uh as the there
we go and we use the dead zone instead
of that so that we can control if we
want to use the other stick at some
point we can use it uh and then we have
the result uh equal to the value as well
so that is basically all there is to it
nothing more uh and then we can return
that so there is our processing for the
stick uh looks pretty good I don't know
why that happened that was past bug and
so there we go now we're compiling and I
don't know if we're actually working yet
uh we may not be oh right I can't test
this yet though because that is on
controller one now so what we need to do
is now actually in our code that someday
we'll actually process real controller
input hopefully that'll actually
probably be pretty soon um but basically
what we need to do is set that is analog
uh so that's set to true and we need to
actually check that controller uh so
basically what we're going to do here um
is maybe uh we will just flat out check
all the controllers in a for Loop uh
right here so basically we'll say uh
controller index equals zero uh we will
go ahead and oops that's no good switch
to overwrite mode accidentally uh we'll
basically just check all the controllers
like this so that we'll we'll pick up
because we were only picking up the
keyboard now because it's controller
zero so I'd rather just do uh this I'll
change uh input zero to be controller
like that and uh we will go ahead and
grab every controller in a loop and for
each controller will basically just do
the operations uh directly for each one
now that basically won't work for tone
herts tone HTS will get overwritten so
uh the last controller whoever the last
controller is to report is analog will
overwrite tone
Hertz but that's okay for now we don't
really care about
that there we we go looks pretty good
nice and stable and that dead zone
processing seems to be working as well
there's no Jitter there uh we can see as
well when we start up we no longer have
the occasional uh you know joystick is
moving problem uh that looks pretty good
uh I should also check what happens if I
unplug there we go uh it is unplugged
now and now I will plug it back in there
we go uh and
there we
go all right so that looks pretty good
uh however I don't understand I'm not
sure why let me see that that happens
again no it didn't I'm not sure why we
were having that weird tonal thing
happening yeah well seems okay for now
that was a little suspicious I want to
check I when we actually go I guess when
and do sort of more thorough check on
some of this stuff we'll see pretty
quickly if that's right or wrong but
everything else seemed to work properly
so I think we're in good shape uh anyway
uh so that is all I really wanted to do
for that now uh I I want to also make a
couple changes to the way the stick
stuff is handled uh and I uh I thought
about this I was kind of I was lying in
bed and I was thinking and I'm like okay
I was falling asleep and I'm like oh I
should really have done the stick
handling a little
differently I realized there was a
smarter way to do it than what I did at
least I think there is I don't know it's
always every time I write code I try
writing it a little differently to see
if I can get a little better and
sometimes I get worse and sometimes I
don't it's hard to say so I always try
to come up with new ideas and be like oh
maybe let's see what happens if I try
code that looks like this and then I go
and say ah no that didn't work that was
bad or oh there was a good thing there
I'm going to remember that and do that
part thing again uh so what I was
thinking is basically what I'd like to
do is I'd like to treat for this game I
think I'd like to treat the stick as if
it's always essenti
a d-pad and the things are buttons but
then just have an extra piece of data
that says uh what the average motion of
the stick was so that if uh you are
doing sort of motion it can be smooth on
the analog side but you can still use it
you can still look at it as if it was
buttons for the purposes of like double
tap you know like that Dash thing I was
talking about cuz what I realized is the
minmax thing this thing that I was
proposing is actually kind of dumb um
it's way harder for the game to use that
as a thing and it's way harder for that
to capture the thing that we want uh as
compos as opposed to just doing uh
something like this average X right
average y for that stick position uh and
basically that's just only if analog uh
is on will it get those uh and I I could
say that this is uh something like that
right uh basically what I should do is
have these be defined as as as buttons
as well like basically the up down left
right should actually be uh now defined
to be uh buttons the should be d-pad and
buttons should all essentially be
treated the same and that way when you
look for things like Dash in a direction
you just look at the half transition
count for the direction and if the half
transition count is four or whatever or
three I should say you know that that's
a dash that's it uh and you can sum
those over time you look at the half
transition count if you get one half
transition you look at like how many
half transitions you got in say uh a
quarter of a second and that just right
there that tells you what your you know
whether the dude dashed or not uh so I
think I think it's just smarter to do it
that way uh and so maybe what I'll do is
I'll break these up into stick um and uh
and button or something like that right
uh I don't really know if it should be
button it's like I I kind of want
basically like uh act I guess action uh
you know like that kind of thing there's
the action uh and direct and and move I
guess so it's move move in action that's
good I like that move up move down move
left move right and action up action
down action left action right that seems
a little bit more interesting to me uh
and because then that way we basically
have 1 2 3 four five 6 Seven 8 nine 10
of these we basically just have 10
buttons now uh and and the stick average
so hopefully that makes a little bit
sense why I wanted to do that I don't
know if it's a little confusing uh I
apologize but this something I was
thinking about and I was like that's
kind of cool I'm try that uh and then
we'll see when we go to actually make
the movement of our character which will
be pretty soon probably be a couple
weeks when we're when we're actually
doing movement tuning um you'll see how
I use it and and hopefully that'll make
uh a little more sense then too is why I
want to do that I'll be able to show
like okay here's the code of why I think
that was good so I think that's a more
interesting way to do it uh and it means
that basically these become uh
no-brainers the keyboard now gets passed
through totally directly and correctly
since those were um they are essentially
buttons now right and so there's
basically like w is move up right um a
uh is move left uh s is move down and d
uh is move right right uh and then these
are now the uh the action buttons action
up action left action down action right
right um and that is like that's it like
that just works pretty much uh I don't
think that we even really need to do
anything else for the keyboard uh the
keyboard board is is pretty much done
and so then all we have to do is down
here say oh okay that changes a little
bit the way that this thing is handled
basically what we have to decide uh is
what that threshold is for whether it's
moving left right or up or down uh I
guess at first we might say that that
should be just The Dead Zone if you're
outside the dead zone that's a left if
you're outside it's a right so I think I
think that's probably what we want to do
uh so basically what I would say is now
uh we're just going to literally we're
going to get rid of all this mid Max
stuff uh entirely it doesn't need to be
there at all anymore we can directly Set
uh these values so basically we can do
this sort of thing uh let's see
here there we go we can basically
directly pull those uh those sticks and
stuff them into uh stick average X and
stick average Y and that's fine uh but
the other thing we can do then is now
say uh that we are going to use use
these average these stick average things
to determine uh whether there was a uh a
trigger on one of these buttons so
basically what we will do there is say
um I guess uh we would do this we could
even make a
synthetic version of we could even just
call this function really if we wanted
to we could say uh process digital
buttons uh with fake move buttons
essentially uh and then actually just
just full on on pass uh the yeah that's
that's not a bad idea let's try that
I'll say what I'm going to do in a
second here let me just finish
uh Mak making this code change because
we need to actually change these are now
action buttons like that there we go uh
and basically uh I think that's
basically it that looks about right
everything's good there okay uh and we
should probably I feel like these guys
should come in here too while we're
while we're cleaning things up I wonder
if we should go ahead and say uh start
and back are in here as well back and
start so let's do that as well since
we're you know it's free it's this this
is one of the nice things about pulling
out code properly uh is basically you
can just kind of get you can you don't
really have to do much work to start
processing other stuff so there's the
start button uh oops it's get behind my
my head don't want to let that get too
far behind my head or you can't see what
I'm doing so there we go all right uh so
let's go ahead and just throw those in
there while we're at it seems like a
good enough uh reason to do that so this
is stick average X and stick average y
just to get those ported uh we've got
action
down and now we got to clean this up so
that's fine we will clean that up in a
second is there anything else uh the
start button oh that's not good game pad
should probably just be starting back I
would assume is that right yeah so there
we are all ported and now I can just go
ahead and do the thing that I was going
to say uh basically I've already got
this function written that does the
processing for the button exactly the
way I want to so what I'm going to do I
think is just go ahead and use a fake
value as if we had buttons for these
guys and I'll just set that uh I'll just
set that value uh to basically be
whatever to be set properly uh in the
case where the the sticks are in the
position I think they should be and not
if they're not so basically all I'll do
is say uh you know I've got this stick
average X and maybe we'll basically say
I don't know I mean for the purposes of
D of of doing dashes and and treating it
as a button if it's more than halfway I
don't know it's basically like we're
going to have a threshold value
basically right um and we've remapped
things between zero and one now so we
need a value between Z and one so
halfway would be 0.5 right uh and what I
could do is say well if the stick
average X right um is is less uh than
the negative threshold so if it's
negative .5 right uh then then fake move
buttons is one otherwise it's zero right
so it's it's basically in fact all I'm
really doing is is this I'm just doing
that right there that's it uh that's
that's all I'm doing and so I basically
made a fake button bit array that set
you know it's got the bottom bit set in
the case where it suceeded the threshold
and otherwise it doesn't and I'm just
going to say uh basically that move left
which would be stick average x uh you
know if you're moving left and if your
if your stick average X is negative then
you're moving to the left because
negative is mapped this way and positive
is mapped to the right um basically uh I
think that's mostly all I wanted to do
that's that's it uh so yeah and then I
just check for the threshold in the
opposite direction do it for y as well
uh and so now I can just call that same
function which does the counting
properly uh and that's it oops I deleted
my threshold that was a mistake
threshold equals 0.5 uh and that uh reak
32 that's an interesting typo that is
really all I wanted to do for the stick
handling there and it still works fine
on the average now of course we still
can't use the keyboard to control
anything other than just the action
buttons because we're only checking uh
for analog controllers uh in here and so
we need to also make sure that we handle
keyboard controllers so if the
controller is not analog which is the
case of the keyboard what we probably
want to do is say all right um let's
let's process the blue offset at least
uh so we'll say something like um you
know if uh that that controller that
we're looking at here which we know it's
an analog anymore um if it's let's say
um so it's it's stick average so it's if
it's if it's move left uh then we will
go ahead and subtract uh you know
something here we subtract one let's say
uh and if it's if it's move right uh
ended down we'll basically do that so
basically if you're holding any of those
down uh we will we will go ahead and and
update it that way all right there we go
so there there you can see now we've got
our keyboard input working uh awesome
all right uh so I think that's basically
it uh for what I wanted to do input
cleanup let's check the to-dos uh a
little bit here just to make sure uh
that everything is happy about that uh
let's see to do d-pad oh we can knock
out this to do as well with the d-pad we
can just treat the d-pad as another one
um yeah as as basically as as forcing
our stick average if we wanted to right
uh what we could do right here is just
overwrite the stick average with the
d-pad uh in the case where in the case
where someone pushed the d-pad right so
what we can do is say right before we do
this with our stick average right what
we can do is say uh you know let's say
if the if the d-pad up was down right so
they're pushing up uh then we just flat
out set the the stick average y uh to be
negative one right so it's just it's the
fullon it's it's as if you're just
cranking uh all the way although you
know now that I think about it I don't
know which way I don't know I don't know
which way the stick goes does the stick
go is it negative for up or positive for
up I have no idea it should probably be
positive for up shouldn't it uh I don't
know let's find out let's see of course
the documentation doesn't bother to tell
you because why would you do that right
let's see here left each TR see see okay
so they just put it in the wrong place
so it does tell us negative value
signify down down or to the left so
negative is down so stick average y
should be positive if the up button is
pressed right makes some sense uh we'll
go ahead and flat out overr right um the
with down as well right makes sense
hopefully this is self-explanatory all
I'm doing is basically overwriting the
stick value with the d-pad in the case
that the user used the d-pad because of
course if you moved your hand off and
started using the d-pad we'd want to use
that uh because if you were trying to
use the stick presumably you wouldn't be
fussing with the d-pad um so it seems
like a pretty lowrisk way to to allow
you to use the d-pad and not have you
have to pick you can just use whichever
one you want at any time and switch
between them uh which seems preferable
so I should be able to do that and now I
should actually be able to use the d-pad
uh for stuff as well which I can there
we go all right all right that's good uh
so let's take a look at this here uh
what else do we have
um yeah uh oops that's not good all
right so here stick average y i i did
the negative I I I forgot to take the
negative out on the positive case so
that's not that's not fun at all all
right so there's our move left okay uh
so basically I think I don't know I got
maybe I might have some more bugs in
here did that pretty quickly uh
obviously we're going to have to test
this uh and we will be able to test it
very easily once we actually have the
game up and running we'll draw out the
stick positions and kind of go through
run run through a little test to make
sure that it all moves the way that it
should move and basically um yeah I
think that's a about it uh that too is
about polling which we will do a little
later uh let's see here um and I think
we don't have a to-do we should have
another to-do in here um to-do Casey
need
to not pull uh disconnected controllers
to avoid X input frame rate hit on older
libraries so so we know
uh that that needs to happen as well I
will be showing that how to do that much
later in the Stream but yeah so anyway
uh I think that is
mostly uh all we needed to do we have
our keyboard input going uh we have our
to-dos out of there for things uh these
are all to-dos that we're going to be
doing for other stuff we could make that
zero memory thing uh let's see need to
not pull disconnected controllers to
avoid xinput frame rate hit on all the
libraries that's in there yes we'll do
that uh pack that will check the packet
number when we do that and that that
looks pretty good that looks pretty good
I suppose there's one thing we could do
uh more while we're just in here just in
case it makes our life a little bit
easier later uh which is we could also
have is connected um basically uh so
that we can set whether or not there
actually is something on there we might
as well throw that in now and that way
when we're testing things we can
actually test that as well just as a
little like you know get things working
in the game and so that it actually does
uh the right thing there so basically
what we can do is say all right um the
new keyboard controller is always
connected because we're just assuming
that there's a keyboard later on we'll
do stuff with that where we actually
pull for multiple keyboards and all
kinds of fun stuff like this but for now
we know we just always have one keyboard
and that's fine uh and here uh we
basically know that this is connected if
we get it so new controller uh is
connected let's see new controller is
connected is true in here uh whereas it
is not true in here right so there we go
so I think that's it I think that's
it that is looking good my friends that
is looking good uhoh that's no good that
is not looking good uh that's not good
at all uh what is our what did we do we
made we made an we made a grievous error
people um and that is that is not what
we should be doing uh
that is unfortunate all right so
basically we have uh I let me just
before we go look at that I wanted to I
want to verify what we're doing here
make sure of things kosher so we did
everything that we need to do for our
keyboard controllers that's all fine uh
we got the input and that's nice um we
should in theory always have the right
number of controllers do we have that uh
I should also put in some assertions
here one thing that I would like to do
uh as well is for getting the
controllers out uh I'd like to go ahead
and make a thing for that I'll show you
what I mean by that uh I want to
basically make a thing uh in fact I can
just write it right here something like
this uh get controller uh and you pass
it the game input and then I just say
controller index out of that and
basically the only reason I wanted to do
that was basically to make a bounds
check uh to basically just make sure
that people aren't asking for Stuff uh
that's that's out of bounds so basically
what I'm going to do is just assert when
we call that uh that the array count of
the input controllers is correct because
we're starting to be a little fiddly
there and I want to sort of make sure
that that's uh not going to cause a
problem basically we do that and then
assuming that it is uh then we will
basically just access the array so this
is not this is literally just putting in
the kind of thing that uh this is
basically like higher level languages
often do this for you automatically like
balance checking and just give you an
error we can do this pretty trivially
for our own arrays people who write C++
might make a templated class for these
sorts of things that do balance checking
and we'll be doing some stuff for that
later as we kind of get further on into
making our own uh sorts of Library stuff
but for now we kind of have to do it the
oldfashioned way uh which is basically
just to do uh the check ourself so here
we go ahead and say uh we've got the
controller index and that is there we
pass the result back uh and that should
be good uh like that and basically all I
want to do is just now make it uh so
that everyone has to go through that so
what I'm going to do here is a little
trick that I like to use which is
basically like insert a bogus character
into the definition of something to see
where it is used so that basically I can
just go through all my code that was
accessing that directly before uh and
basically not access it directly if I
don't think it should be accessed
directly uh so I look at each individual
one and this for example is getting it
so I rather do uh get controller here
pass it the input and the controller
index and have that return the value
right um
same thing with these guys those should
be get controller pass it the thing and
the index like so same thing here get
controller new input pass the value back
right and so that's just you know again
this is just basically uh checking for
bugs in in making it easier for us to
find them especially because we have a
bounds over right we got to go find in a
second here uh that's this is the sort
of code we need to start putting in to
make sure that we don't make uh stupid
mistakes uh yeah when we're doing stuff
so there we go and we'll get controller
here new input our controller index
there we are uh and let's take a look oh
yeah well I already spotted the bounds
over right that's kind of obvious uh you
can you can see what what's going on
here that's that was just wrong actually
uh what we needed this computation was
wrong you know
what I I will explain it fully I
shouldn't go fixing things before I
actually say what I'm fixing I saw what
the error was cuz I kind kind of knew
where the error was going to be and it
was there so I we'll we'll push that for
a second and this is actually I'd rather
I'd rather have the nice demo of showing
you that this balance checking was
valuable so I shouldn't I was I was I'm
I'm I'm spoiling my own punchline who
wants to spoil their own punch line
that's that's just silly right we don't
we don't wish to spoil our own punch
lines we list we wish to have uh our
punch lines land at exactly the right
time all right so I think that was uh
everybody um
what's going on here hello emac come
back there we go uh all right so we'll
we'll go ahead and build that there we
go and we should bam right there that is
exactly what we wanted you can see that
our assertion has caught the error and
the error is that this controller access
is out of bounds um it is passing a
controller index that's too high so why
is it doing that it's because when I was
fussing with that routine I sort of
slapped in something that's just totally
erroneous basically what we want to do
here uh is we want to make sure uh that
we don't go above uh the controller
value uh that that is um we don't want
to sample controllers that would be
outside our range so we are saying that
we'll support One keyboard and and four
gamepads that was sort of what we were
saying the game might might allow for
input so we have five input slots so
what we want to do is make sure that
xuser Max count never actually goes
above that and so what I wanted to do
was clip that here so what we could say
is um the way I was saying is 1 plus Max
user count that will end up U making it
equal five so this will actually be a
loop of five which then adds one to the
controller index which allows it to
write uh to actually the sixth entry
that's no good that's just a bug uh what
we actually wanted to do here is still
only count up to four uh because we're
already doing the increment by one so
this needs to clip this needs to be x uh
X um user Max count and we basically
need to make sure that the max
controller count is actually
equal to this value minus one we need to
be like uh less than the array bounds
minus the keyboard size right that's
what we were actually trying to do uh so
that was kind of just a silly that was
just that was just a mistake and so now
we should be back to goodness and you'll
notice we don't get the assertion
anymore so that was good uh and I think
that basically finishes up I don't think
we've got anything left uh to do uh
really there that seems like we've got
everything we have all of our inputs oh
you know one thing we could do in the
last seconds here of as the stream is
about over uh is we could go ahead and
map uh escape to be uh back that back
button uh and and uh and and or the
start button let's say and back could be
a space I don't I don't know what we
want we've got the shoulder buttons for
q&e uh and then I don't know I guess um
uh back and start back back could be
backspace I don't know what on the
keyboard should be mapped to the back
button uh maybe the space bar I don't
know let's I don't know we'll just we're
just going to map these and we'll change
them uh when if we need to so so there
we go just so we have those in there all
right everyone we ended right on time
and we did exactly what we wanted to do
today which is clean up our input so now
we have keyboard input and stick input
going through properly handling the dead
zone you can use the d-pad you can use
the analog stick uh we even are tracking
transitions uh for using things like
Double Dash so I think uh I am pretty
happy with that now we may have some
bugs in there because we haven't tested
it very thoroughly yet and we will be
doing that kind of in the game code
we'll actually put the test stuff in
there because we're going to want our
test stuff to be shared across the
different platforms right so you can
fire up your Mac port or whatever and
take a look and make sure the stick's
working there as well so we'll take care
of that in the in the platform code next
week uh but for right now I'm feeling
pretty good about that that looks pretty
good I don't have any reservations about
what we've done there we eliminated a
bunch of to-dos uh we still got some in
here that we should probably take a look
at but basically we're down to just a
couple things tomorrow we'll focus on
the frame timing uh and then we'll kind
of go through here and clean up a some
of these other ones uh we'll focus on
that see if we can get frame timing done
tomorrow uh if it might spill into
Thursday and then Friday will kind of be
a general cleanup day and I think we
might make it we might finish up all of
our 132 stuff and be in real good shape
uh by the end of the week which would be
pretty awesome um basically the 20 hour
completely explained uh win32 game
prototyping layer
uh is is is a pretty darn good thing I
think we should all be pretty proud of
ourselves if you're not proud of
yourselves out there well you should be
uh because I think we did uh a lot of
stuff in a short amount of time and we
kept it very concise and the code is
looking pretty clean um again the
important part like I said is it doesn't
matter how gross this win32 layer is
either um we don't have to care about
that cuz interfacing with Windows is
going to be a little gross all we want
to make sure is that this is clean this
is nice and clean so that our game can
be nice and clean and it is I think
looking uh pretty nice so far such a
clean boundary uh so I'm pretty excited
about that going forward I think it's
going to be pretty cool so with that
said uh we will now go to the questions
please make sure you put cator in the
question when you ask it so I will see
it on the little
filter uh
and also uh if you could keep the
questions to code we did today or in
some previous day not about code we're
going to do in the future because we
will be doing the code in the future and
I will probably answer the questions in
the course of actually uh showing you
how to do that code so with that let's
go to the questions let's take a look uh
at what's going on let's
see so it looks like maybe some people
caught a bug or typo they were saying
maybe there was all move lefts uh what's
going on
here trying to read back through the
stream check the array in the buttons
Union might want 12 now that you've
added start and back oh right yes thank
you that is a good point uh because we
want to be able to handle all these I
wish there was a way so okay let's think
about this for a second it'd be
interesting to know is there a good way
we could make sure that we could catch
this bug like when we add stuff in here
and we want this array to have all the
things right uh and so what we want to
do there is basically we want to do
something like when we come in at uh
well this actually should be
crossplatform uh so when in here uh we
want to do something where we can sort
of assert uh that for example I guess
the address of the last button we know
about right so button start equals the
add equals the um the length of this
kind of thing I don't know if that makes
sense but basically like we might want
to say let's assert uh that say input uh
let's see input
controllers zero start um
that is uh equal to um well I guess how
can I do that I could
subract yeah so so I okay so I guess
what I would say is let's say that start
the address of
start this is going to be pretty janky
the address of start uh plus one so I'm
going I'm going forwards a little bit
there the address the the address of
start plus one uh or well okay okay the
address of start let's do it this way
take the address add of the start button
subtract it from the address uh of the
move button uh like this well I could
even just do button zero right that the
address of button zero uh that should
equal uh the array count of the buttons
like
that
so right uh now it's going to be off by
one because it's actually should be one
past that uh so it should be the array
count of the buttons I believe minus one
that's that's the actual check I think
game controller input does not have oh
right sorry don't need it that is actual
structure so basically I'm trying to do
is do some po arithmetic here and let's
see if that works yes good that caught
it of course I'm not sure if it's
actually still correct but that caught
it and then it should be 12 now let's
see if that works properly off we go
yeah so basically what I did here was I
just wrote something I said all right
let's take where the start button is in
the layout of the structure let's
subtract the base of the button array
from it which is the the start of this
whole thing right and I want to make
sure that the number that I get back is
equal to 11 right the number I want it
to equal the the uh array count of these
minus one because again we're using the
pointer to start is going to point to
just before the start button structure
right it's pointing to the start of it
so if I subtract it from the base I'm
going to get one less than the total
count that there are um and so I'm just
checking to make sure that matches now
this isn't perfect because we can still
do
this and this won't catch it right that
makes sense um but it at least checks uh
that the last button that we know about
in here uh is is correct now we could do
something else uh we could use a get
button function that checked I don't
know if I want to go that route uh I'm
also not sure if there's any way oh you
know duh I've got one way we could do it
there's a pretty easy way we can do it
in fact uh we could just do this I
suspect
uh game controller input buttons duh why
not do it this way can I do that I don't
know if I can do that yeah uh oh no I
guess it has to be anonymous it's not
going to let me name it is
it yeah that's too bad I was hoping it
would let me name it because if it let
me name it then we could just say the
size of this thing um but I can't do
that at the moment unfortunately and
still keep it Anonymous which is what we
kind of wanted to do now we could go and
make it non Anonymous we could make it
be a thing that actually has a name
right and we access off the name I don't
know if we really want to do that um
seems like a little inconvenient but
maybe it's better to keep the bugs uh
you know if if I basically said this
then we could just do the assertion that
that this structure was the same size as
this array which is kind of what we
would like to
do
[Music]
H well one other thing we could do is we
could do something uh like this I'm not
happy with any of
these
really we could insert a fake button it
doesn't mean anything at all uh and then
we could just say well it's that button
uh is it's got to be equal to that the
array size right so it's like a
Terminator button and now if if we go in
and add a button as long as we don't add
it below the Terminator right if we
always add our buttons up here uh then
that assert uh will fire properly for us
right bam and it's and it caught the
error uh so maybe that's good for now I
don't know have to think about that
maybe we do want to just name it and
deal with the name so we can do it more
cleanly uh so I'll do note Casey all
buttons must must be added above this
line for now and that's that's something
so we'll leave it like that for now but
thank you for catching that error uh
because that was a good one that would
have been
annoying uh let's
see there's a lot of questions we're not
going to get to all these there's too
many
questions
um is that that some copy
pasta or is it really supposed to be all
move
lefts I don't no uh so is there
somewhere that it's actually uh actually
wrong where we're doing move left uh
multiple times and shouldn't
be yes that is copy pasta that is
totally copy pasta thank you for that so
basically I just for missed these here
um uh uh d-pad oh we didn't test the
d-pad yet right because we ran out time
so we would have found this as as soon
as we we tested the d-pad I was like how
come we didn't see that but that's why
we haven't done that yet uh so basically
I just need to go ahead and make these
be the actual values that they should be
let's see here uh oh we said down was
negative that's what the documentation
said so down oops down is negative uh
get out of my way so I don't hit my head
pun intended so yeah that was just copy
pasta that was supposed to be that and I
iess I can test that now too can't I I
can test the d-pad there we
go yeah yeah uh should be right yeah
okay um well oh you know what no I take
it back so the reason we didn't catch
that is we did test the d-pad the reason
we didn't catch that is that's just for
the button we we don't have anything
that test those values that's just for
the thing for checking like Dash and
that sort of stuff so yeah unfortunately
that yeah that unfortunately is not
actually going to uh that's not going to
help us so we're going to actually have
to test that later we still don't know
if that's working properly we'll have to
test that later you know what else we
should do uh while we're on the subject
of things that could happen uh another
thing we should do is maybe fake the
stick average I don't know we could n
let's not let's not do that that's
Dum well okay so let me just let me just
tell you what I'm thinking here so when
we use the d-pad we should probably
change to say that the thing is not
analog anymore right um I don't know
don't you think like that way it knows
like if we see input from the d-pad the
game should probably switch to using the
same kind of control scheme as it's
using on the keyboard where it would do
like smoothing and stuff for you so I
feel like maybe we want to set this to
false if we do any of this nonsense I
think I'm going to leave that
in all right let's
see could it good to apply some
integration on the digital keys so we
don't just set the value to Binary
ne11
um that's a good question I don't think
so because the way I want this to work
is I basically want the um I'm only
setting the stick average so that it
sets the move left move right move down
move up buttons uh and then I'm setting
the is analog uh and I'm going to let
the game use the is analog flag to say
oh I'm going to start using buttons now
instead of the analog stick for this
controller until it goes back to using
the analog stick uh and I'm hoping that
that will kind of uh be the thing that
works best there now it's a little bit
tricky uh because it's like well you
know we probably also don't want to set
is analog to True unless the stick is
actually being used something like this
uh so if the stick average is not equal
to zero um uh or the if the sck average
in either direction right excuse me is
not equal to zero something like that
that is more like okay now we've got you
know now we've got something
where the game really does know whether
using the analog stick or the d-pad at
any given time and it should do so that
integration that you're talking about to
smooth out using the digital that's
that's will be done by the game because
it's going to have to do that for the
keyboard as well so we want to make that
Unified
can you talk about the dead zone being
round versus rectangular and at Hardware
usb hid and X
input uh oh you're saying who I'm not
sure what you mean by at Hardware usb
hid and xinput API layers so as far as I
know the dead zone is literally
something that's only software side like
the hardware is reporting just like its
potentiometer values or whatever it's
get what I don't know what they do use
nowadays but whatever ever they're
reading they're just reporting that
electrical level like turned into
something uh and so when you get back
the short it's just a like Quant it's
some kind of quantization of the
electrical level and so as far as I know
on USB it that's just on the US on the
bus uh it's just getting pasted uh as
part of the hid page like here's an X
you know here's a here's a a linear maap
value and here it is as far as I know
I've never actually gone and looked at
what the hid code Pages look like for
these but I think it's basically just
passes that value through X simp hands
it to us and then it's up to us to
basically do that dead zone processing
and xinput has pound defined what it
says the spec is for The Dead Zone on
the controller but I think that's it I
don't think there's anything else to it
uh as for round versus
rectangular I know nothing about that I
know that they have defined it to be
rectangular um and I guess that pretty
much makes sense if you think about it
uh I don't know the inner construction
of this thing but if you imagine that
there's essentially two potentiometers
or two whatever they use like I said to
read it one for the horizontal one for
the vertical then they're both going to
have their own error and that error is
not going to be circular right it's not
going to be based on how far you've gone
to the left necessarily whether the Y is
going to be more or less error if
they're read independently the error
could very well be rectangular and so if
the error is rectangular then you don't
have much of a choice but to clip the
error rectangularly now what we can do
in our own code uh is we can go and try
to do some better Dead Zone processing
if we find it to be a problem uh this
again is the first pass on the input
stuff and so we'll have to go look and
see um basically what what we think once
we're playing it uh whether we think
it's working well enough for our game or
not and if it's not we may have to do
more um fancier stuff uh you know like
Bas like like uh grad like changing how
this works in a sort of gradual sense uh
so that basically when you come out of
the dead zone that's at zero and it
eases in instead of right now when you
come out of the Dead Zone you're going
to be at 0.2 right because we know the
dead that's where the dead zone is so
you're going to be the lowest value you
can report for movement is 0.2 so maybe
we don't want that maybe we want that it
to be clipped down and to do the dead
zone processing in a different way right
like you could
imagine I don't know if we want to do
this but you could imagine
uh I maybe we should do this I don't
know I mean I don't know what do you
guys think what I'm trying to say here
is what we could do is it might be
better to have that value go smoothly
from 0 to one instead of jumping up to
0.2 right so I guess what I'm proposing
is you know one thing we could do to
make the dead zone processing work a
little better is we could basically say
well all right uh we essentially know
that Negative Dead Zone threshold is not
counted so we need to reenter our value
uh so that basically
um The Dead Zone threshold is a
subtracted away from the divisor right
uh and the value itself
which is of course negative has Dead
Zone added to it to bring it up to zero
in the appropriate uh scenario right
this is this is what I'm talking about
does this make sense I don't know if any
if if this makes any sense to anyone I'm
just sort of proposing this uh as a
thing uh that we could do right uh does
this make sense so basically what I'm
saying here is normally what would
happen and I can go to the diagram for
this uh just to make it a little clearer
go to the diagram because there is
actually only one we've actually just
always had the same version of paint up
and I just clear it every time so
they're literally there is the diagram
basically what I was saying is you know
we've got this scenario where basically
there's a dead zone here and we've got
stick values and those stick values
start being you know whatever they are
right um this sort of thing and we're
basically saying that anything in here x
input has told us is noisy right we
can't we can't count sck values in here
as actually being valid movement that
the player was trying to do because it's
just random noise uh on the line so what
happens is uh if we look at the stick
position right inside the dead zone as
it moves outside let's say he's moving
the stick to the right so he moves it in
this direction right what are each of
these values right here's the dead zone
value and I guess we said that was 25%
so here's maximum right what we might
want to do it if we map it just directly
so that this right here is zero and this
right here is 1.0 I got my head in the
way there a little bit don't I let's try
this
again let's try this again without the
Casey head
right so if I'm looking at the x- axis
right if I'm looking at at this span
here uh I could map this end to zero and
this end to one right but what would
happen there is as the user moves the
stick like this when he crosses the
boundary when that boundary when the
when the player crosses the boundary
it's going to jump right from being zero
which is what we were reporting for the
whole time it was in The Dead Zone to
being essentially 0. 2 or somewhere
around there right 0.25 something like
that right it's going to jump right to
0.25 so the only values that the game
will ever see are between 0.25 and one
which is kind of confusing to the game
if you think about it and basically then
the whole game would have to be tuned
assuming that the lowest value is 0.25
on the stick which doesn't make a whole
lot of sense so what I was saying is
well let's subtract The Dead Zone
variable the The Dead Zone area away and
just treat just this range here as 0 to
one right um that's what I was trying to
do uh I don't know if that makes sense
let's see here let's
see hopefully that makes some
sense all right uh so so yeah I don't
know if that makes sense or not or if if
it if it's if it's not an appropriate
way to do it someone was saying they
actually do uh have a round Dead Zone
defined let's see if that's actually
true um let's see here if it's actually
round Dead Zone we can do this even
better uh let's see round Dead Zone Dead
Zone
um can be used as positive to filter
something because they don't actually
say
here they don't actually say well okay
we can do some extra reading we don't
have a whole lot of time left in the
Stream we can do some extra reading to
see whether it's round dead zone or a
non-round dead zone it's been a long
time since I've read any xinput
documentation so let's just do both and
then we'll just use whichever one we
find to be correct so let's say this is
round Dead Zone value if it's round Dead
Zone value then that basically means the
total length of the motion on the stick
is subject to that dead zone right I
don't know if that makes sense uh so
basically what we would have to do is
we'd have to do the dead zone processing
in a as a pair right we basically have
to say we're going to do a dead zone
processing on the actual Vector value uh
so that would be something here that
would have to look uh like well yeah
that's going to have to be Vector you
know what that's going to if that's true
uh and and maybe that is true we could
go we could go look and see uh so this
is something that we got I'm not going
to be able to explain that in 10 minutes
because I have to introduce the concept
of ukian length and there's no way
that's happening in 10 minutes that's
just unrealistic uh so basically what
I'll say is to do uh this this is a
square Dead Zone uh check X input to
verify that the dead zone is circular
someone was posting a link so I'm
assuming that they checked it on the
stream and that it is circular or well
or I guess we could say round this is uh
the dead zone is round and show how to
do round Dead Zone processing but yeah
that's uh that's too it's too bad it's
round it's actually better for gameplay
if it's round so I hope you're right um
about that because that would be nice
and the only thing that's the downside
there it's going to take me longer to
explain how to do round Dead Zone
processing so yeah but thank you for
writing into that because I was not sure
about that since the documentation here
didn't say as we were reading it um and
that's really all I had to go on um
we'll we'll have to find some some uh
some documentation on The Dead Zone let
me let me check that page I out maybe
that page before had it and we'll see if
they say that it's round Dead
Zone and then we could uh we could know
assuming that this documentation is
correct which of course we also don't
know just because it says one way or the
other it doesn't actually mean anything
if we don't check it we should probably
check it as well so let's take a look
here uh The Dead
[Music]
Zone okay yeah yeah yeah blah blah
blah let's
see not really saying yet we can look at
the example and assume that that's
correct but
uh circular dead zone
uh well it says it allows the
enforcement of a circular Dead Zone but
does it actually say that it is a
circular Dead
Zone
[Music]
um uh yeah
so unfortunately I guess you know what
we'll just we'll just table this for now
and we'll get someone who actually knows
for sure I will try to contact someone
who would know for sure because this
just says their processing is a circular
Dead Zone but that doesn't mean that the
hardware has has a circular Dead Zone
The Dead Zone might still be rectangular
in which case us processing as it
circular is only making it worse so we
kind of need to actually know whether
the input dead zone is literally
circular on the
controller uh and if that makes sense so
I don't know I don't know yeah because
they're they're processing it circular
but that doesn't mean anything that just
means that they're processing it at
circular but they don't say that the
hardware was made with a circular de
Zone CU if the hardware still has a
rectangular Z Zone doesn't help us does
that make sense I don't know if that
makes sense I don't know if that makes
sense uh but there's some links in here
so we'll check them
out uh let's
see I'm 16 days behind is there a better
way to catch up than watching all the
days on YouTube yes there is but only
slightly uh obviously everything is
important uh so you got to watch it all
but uh if you go to the news inform
Forum if you go to handmad her.org and
go to the news and forums link there's a
thing called episode guide uh that has
better uh annotation on it so you can go
to something uh like this and it's got
jump it allows you to jump around the
stream so that is better uh than the
than the YouTube uh uh system but it's
still all just watching the YouTube but
it does like to skip things you already
know and that sort of stuff all right
uh boy there's a lot of questions on
here I'm going to miss some for the
buildup at you can build for Windows XP
64bit using 5.2 instead of 5.1 uh but we
don't actually need to do that uh
because it's already building for for
5.2 also the inline method for get
controller what happens if you pass in
negative one for index uh so you can if
you want to uh for this they were
basically saying should we check against
those you almost never have that bug you
can if you want to uh you can you can do
one of two things you can either do this
right uh which now makes it so that you
know the value is always unsigned so if
they did pass a negative one it would
fail this array count by being way high
it would be FF it' be like you know uh
four four billion or whatever uh so you
can do that or you can assert that
controller index uh is greater than
equal to zero whichever one floats your
boat uh but that's that's
basically I mean that's that's the long
and short of it you almost never have
buffer underruns though uh at least I
don't I very very rarely have buffer
underruns so checking against them is
not so important important buffer
overruns you often I find that just the
nature of the way that c code tends to
work you are very likely to write a
buffer overrun you are just not that
likely to write a buffer underrun
because you rarely sub go backwards with
pointers I don't know that's just it's
weird it's a bias it doesn't really have
to be that way but that is just the way
that code typically gets
written um let's
see can you do struct inner buttons type
and still get the benefit yeah so that
was what I was trying to do before so
for some reason uh buttons type like
this sort of thing it did not work
um at least it didn't seem to uh yeah
basically like giving it a name ruins
the anonymousness of it and makes it so
that you can't access the interior uh by
without going through it first so
basically you have to do it that way as
far as I can tell um
yeah I just don't know I I don't know
any other way to do it unfortunately
there there probably is a C++ 11 e way I
would think but I'm not
sure I don't get using win 32 prefix or
function names but compiling to 64bit
okay uh so basically that's just to tell
us that this so this code isn't actually
windows 64bit it's Windows 32 uh bit
that you can compile as 64-bit so
actually all of the this stuff and we
showed this on the last stream all of
this stuff can be compiled for win32 as
well as win64 so it is not win64 code it
is Win 32 code but we can compile in 64-
bit when we want to which we do want to
because that's uh going to be faster so
basically uh it's called win32 because
it actually is all win32 clean code
there's nothing in here that requires
win64 so we are compiling for both and
that's why the win32 if we had a
function that only worked on wi64 then
we'd call it
wi64 uh let's
see let's
see I was thinking about for game
processing input in a separate thread so
it is frame rate independent but I heard
you could introduce input lag is that
true uh we are we are probably going to
do some pulling potentially in separate
thread as well it does not introduce
input lag uh it would if you did it
poorly I guess uh but as long there
there really isn't any reason
uh I strongly suspect that we will want
to potten that at least for educational
purposes if not for any real reason do a
separate thread for input polling say
pulling the X input sticks and as far as
I know there is no reason why we can't
Implement that with no lag um I I cannot
think of any reason in my head why that
would have to be laggy I may be
forgetting something but basically it
would just stuff it in a queue and the
other thing and the main throw pull it
out of the queue and you could do a lock
free queue even for something as simple
as that so there really wouldn't be
there would literally not even be a
mutex around it so I don't feel like
there should be any lag if you did it
poorly there'd be a bunch of lag but if
you did it properly I I don't think
there should
be you said a circular Dead Zone would
be good for gameplay why don't you just
make it circular The Dead Zone would
just be a little bit bigger well the
reason is because then you're just
losing information right um basically
like this is why I say I actually want
to know what the hardware does because I
want to actually provide as much data as
the hardware gives me so if the hardware
was specified this way um then I want to
pass that to the game I don't want to uh
circumscribe a circle like this and take
a bunch of valid data that the game
could have been getting and throw it out
I'm saying it's better for gameplay
because a circle means that you have the
same resolution no matter what direction
you're going in so you don't lose
resolution on the stick as you go out
here so I'm just saying the joystick is
better if it's circular uh assuming that
it's still if it's if so an inscribed
circle is better than this which is why
I want to know uh so basically you're
saying my if if to be 100%
explicit basically we've got some
measurement of the stick we're saying
that measurement is noisy it's not
accurate so what I want to know is is
the noise on both axis so we have a
certain bit of noise on this axis and a
certain bit of noise on this axis which
leads to this dead zone literally on the
hardware in which case that is how we
should process it or are we saying that
it's just the total distance that is
noisy it's just however far you moved it
so no matter what direction you move it
in it's still the same amount of noise I
find that hard to believe it doesn't
sound like how Hardware normally works
but my knowledge of joysticks is from
like
1990 so that could very well be possible
nowadays maybe they've got better
techniques for building joysticks so
what I would like to do I'm not going to
go by the msdn code because all that
said was we're going to process it a
circular Dead Zone but who cares that's
not relevant right we don't care how
they process it we care what the
hardware does so what I'd like to do is
actually go talk to somebody who knows
the hardware intimately and say what
actually what is the actual noise
profile of this hardware and I'd like to
process it that way that makes sense
uh so we're basically out of time here
just trying to quickly see uh let's see
here let's see
here
um I don't think there's any more
[Music]
questions uh that I can get
to um
looks like mostly everything
straightforward we could cover it looks
like mostly just discussion of circular
versus uh rectangular Dead Zone and I
want to go actually get some
verification of how the hardware Works
before I do that but if it does then
we'll just do a circular Dead Zone we
might postpone that till I talk about
vectors so we may have to postpone
circular Dead Zone processing if it it
does turn out to be circular until I
talk about vectors but that's about
it um let's see
yeah uh
yeah some of these questions are good
maybe I'll just do let me do an extra
five or 10 minutes here because some of
these questions are good uh there's a
question about direct input versus X
input X input is easier direct input
supports more devices so if you want to
support older Hardware you need to use
either direct input or you need to go
off the raw input or the hid system
which one we do I won't know I don't
know but we probably should support
direct input as well as X input in the
end just so we can support older devices
or we can just say ah it doesn't really
matter it's just an exercise in win32
programming and maybe that's not a
useful thing to teach on the stream I
don't know yes direct input is much
Messier uh no there isn't much point to
it but the bottom line is that X input
just does not support Legacy devices so
people who have old gamepads they won't
work unless you use xinput or they can
run a program sometimes that Max maps
direct input to X input um but it's
nicer if you do do it nicely for them
right
so there's
that um let's see
here let's see
here
um
uh I deleted the Min and Max Mac uh yes
that's true I did I had said that I kind
of wanted to so if you remember uh
basically uh in The Dead Zone processing
I was using uh the the I I sort of said
I wish I should use a Min and Max here
but I didn't have one yet uh and so that
was in uh that was in this code so right
here I was saying I could use that I
don't think it's relevant anymore
because especially if we change to a
circular Dead Zone then it's not
relevant anymore um so I think we don't
actually need that to do anymore but
thank you for catching that that that
could have been appropriate uh we'll get
to M and Max macros at some point
certainly
uh yes
yes
um so when you use a zero controller why
don't you just do star new keyboard
controller equals brackets so the answer
is because I don't think that used to
work um Let me let me show you what the
person was talking about they were
saying uh when you do this uh can you
just do that and C++ 11 may allow that
uh yeah it does but I'm pretty sure that
didn't used to work
um I'm kind of torn as whether how much
of those sorts of newer features we
should be using um but I guess if
someone was implementing compiler this
is a pretty easy thing to do just the
fact that that clears something so I'm
okay with that so yeah I I'm I'm fine
with that that's totally cool uh I don't
have a problem with that uh yeah we'll
we'll go with that we'll go with that uh
I I can I can live with that I can be
happy with
that
[Music]
um let's
see looks like someone was asking about
normalizing to The Dead Zone to Max
short thing which is actually something
I just did so yes I whoever made that
suggestion that is a very good
suggestion that is exactly what I
thought should be good um let's see
here uh
[Music]
um standard death should include offset
of you could use that to make your
assert a little simpler that's true but
I'd rather just stick with the point
arithmetic so we don't introduce more
overhead there maybe I don't know if
we'll use offset of in the future we
might uh basically there's a there's a a
macro you can do um called offset of
I'll show you the docs for it here
actually so offset of which simplifies
some of the stuff that I was doing uh
where is a good reference here it is so
basically there's a macro called offset
of and what offset does of is it takes
the name of a type and then it takes the
name of a member inside that type and it
Returns the the Delta between the base
of the structure the start of the
structure and that type so it's the
offset inside the structure so this code
that I had here right and I'll just go
ahead and do it um I'm fine with using
offset of I don't have a problem with
that I guess but uh basically if I
wanted to I could make this use less uh
it could less or Bose by basically
saying like Okay um really all we need
to know is just the game controller
input instead of having to give a
reference to it I just want to say that
Terminator right uh minus the offset of
uh the buttons array there right oops
that's not good minus offset
of uh game controller
input here we go
buttons that uh is essentially uh
equivalent to what I had written before
I don't know if that makes sense um I
don't I don't really think there's any
reason to do it and since I have to use
the other one for array count anyway
although I could actually write array
count in front I think I'd rather just
leave it the way that it was
personally
personally uh let's see let's
see
um anything
else anything else that I
missed
um so we'll get we'll look at the
circular Dione later so I'm not ignoring
that we will we will absolutely I'll
check uh later tonight actually to see
if I can find someone who can say
definitively what the hardware does Dead
Zone wise um but let's take a look so is
there anything else looks pretty good I
think we've covered just about
everything that is relevant to today's
code um yeah
yeah all right uh so thank you everyone
for joining us um sorry there were so
many questions there that it was hard to
make sure we got all of them I think I
got all of them related to what we do uh
and I want to table the circular Dead
Zone thing it's important uh because I
do want to model the hardware accurately
so it's very important I don't want you
to think we're skipping over it we will
find out whether it's circular or
rectangular Dead Zone and we will adjust
accordingly uh but even if it is
circular I going to say I'm afraid I'm
going to have to probably table that for
another two weeks till we can do talk
about vectors uh because you really I
you really need utility and length uh to
do a circular Dead Zone I can't think of
any way to do it without that so we're
going to have to to get to that point
before we can process C Dead Zone but
we'll find out which one it is I will
track down someone who knows for sure
how these how these controllers are made
internally find out whether they have
circular or rectangular dead zones and
then we will go from there that said
thank you very much for joining me for
another edition of handmade hero I am
very pleased with the progress we made
today we have our input layer looking
much better than it was before probably
still some bugs in there because we
haven't tested it and you always have
bugs until you test uh so we need to do
more testing and we will do more testing
in the future but for now I'm pretty
happy with how we've got designed how
we've got it working I think it's really
good uh and it's going to continue to
get better over time so that's great we
need to work on our frame timing so
that'll be tomorrow and then after that
uh when we get the frame timing done
we're pretty much closed in on just
final cleanup stuff some extra stuff I
want to get in there uh for for for
going forwards with the memory and a
little couple other things so we'll have
a Thursday we'll have stuff to do on
Thursday and Friday as well even if we
do finish up frame coming tomorrow but
we are well within reach of closing out
the entire platform architecture stuff
that we need to do for our first pass
and I am very excited about that I'm
psyched to get to starting to work on
the game next week uh the art is looking
awesome yangin does amazing art and I'm
really excited to start getting it up on
the screen too uh so that's going to be
awesome so thank you everyone for
joining me uh and uh and uh doing
another hour of programming I uh I
encourage you to go to handmad her.org
if you hadn't already um where you can
go to this news and forums button it's
got like a pretty nice Forums on there
people have been posting a lot of great
information uh there's an episode guide
you can use to follow along with the
series and there's annotated notes and
and uh ier does a bunch of illustrations
every week there's just tons of good
stuff on there just go explore and have
fun with it uh it's it's it's some crazy
web stuff that you know I'm not very
good at web stuff so it's a little janky
uh but it works so check that out and of
course if you would like your own copy
of the source code to play around with
uh you can pre-order the game by just
clicking on this button um it handles
both stripe and PayPal so you will get a
link and make sure when you do that make
sure you use a valid email address uh
because basically it sends you a link in
an email that's where you will always go
to redownload the source code every
night because I update it every night so
you want to save that link uh that comes
in the email because that's what allows
you to download the source code and
that's also what allow you to download
the game in the ass so save that uh
every time we do a major uh build
release so as the game goes forwards and
we start doing Milestones I'll send out
an email that has a refresher Link in it
but just make sure you save that for now
so you can always get the source code um
because I don't know much about uh send
out I don't there probably is a way to
kind of just have them resend you your
thing but I just want to make sure
people don't miss it so thank you every
much for joining us uh tomorrow will be
8 p.m. uh Pacific Standard time again I
hope to see you all here it's been
wonderful coding with you and uh it will
be uh I'm really excited to get the
frame uh loop cleaned up tomorrow
because I think that's going to be a lot
of fun too so hope to see you here
tomorrow uh and thank you very much for
joining me